<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>PL on fyshXplore</title>
        <link>http://fyshxfish.github.io/categories/pl/</link>
        <description>Recent content in PL on fyshXplore</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 18:06:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://fyshxfish.github.io/categories/pl/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Foundations and Applications of Intersection and Union Types (PDF)</title>
        <link>http://fyshxfish.github.io/p/foundations-and-applications-of-intersection-and-union-types-pdf/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 18:06:00 +0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://fyshxfish.github.io/p/foundations-and-applications-of-intersection-and-union-types-pdf/</guid>
        <description>&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://fyshxfish.github.io/pdfs/Foundations_and_Applications_of_Intersection_and_Union_Types.pdf&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;750px&#34;&gt;
  Embedde PDF is not supported, &lt;a href=&#34;http://fyshxfish.github.io/pdfs/Foundations_and_Applications_of_Intersection_and_Union_Types.pdf&#34;&gt; please clike here to download.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Safety &amp; Abstraction</title>
        <link>http://fyshxfish.github.io/p/safety-abstraction/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 14:10:00 +0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://fyshxfish.github.io/p/safety-abstraction/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;From &lt;em&gt;Types and Programming Languages § 1.2 What Type Systems Are Good For&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A safe language is one that protects its own &lt;strong&gt;abstractions&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;br&gt;A safe language is completely defined by its programmer&amp;rsquo;s manual.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complete &lt;strong&gt;abstraction&lt;/strong&gt; means that users can fully trust the language design, focusing &lt;strong&gt;only&lt;/strong&gt; on the high-level language abstraction layer, without needing to concern themselves with the specific implementation at the hardware level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-level languages provide abstractions over physical devices. For example, arrays are abstractions over memory. Programmers expect that arrays can &lt;strong&gt;only&lt;/strong&gt; be modified through &lt;strong&gt;explicit&lt;/strong&gt; update operations (e.g., &lt;code&gt;arr[1] = 1024&lt;/code&gt;). &amp;ldquo;Modifying a variable, and some elements in an array are inexplicably changed&amp;rdquo; (e.g., buffer overflow attacks) is a manifestation of broken abstraction. This means that programmers must have a detailed understanding of the layout of variables (abstractions provided by high-level languages) in memory (real physical devices) to write programs that meet expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of a series of experiments in CSAPP. Since the goal of CSAPP is to examine computer systems from the programmer&amp;rsquo;s perspective, i.e., viewing hardware from a software perspective, if the programming language used is safe, then we can fully trust the abstractions it provides. Consequently, we cannot see the hardware through the software. If C were safe, then the experiments in CSAPP couldn&amp;rsquo;t be done 🧐.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
